剛才兒童師班帶給我們一個很重要的訊息
The message that children has brought us today is a very important one
他問我們一個很重要的問題
They ask us a very important question
誰會猜派嬰孩
Who would send a baby
當你看到兒童的時候
When you look at the children
他們很可愛
They are very cute
你很不捨得他們,分開一陣子
If you want, you need to part with them, you don't want to
你不想放他們在任何有危險的機會
Because you don't want to put them in any dangerous situations
誰會猜派自己的嬰孩
So who would actually send his baby
剛才師哥裡面說動盪的世界
So the song said this is a very
difficulties and danger
同時這個世界需要一個拯救者
And this world needs a savior
你會不會就將你自己的嬰孩就去猜去
Would you actually send your own baby to this world
但我們的神
卻是告訴我們回應這個問題
But our God actually responded to this question
剛才我們一開始的時候
施班為我們讀出了
我們這段經文
So in the beginning it was read
因有一嬰孩為我們而生
有一子賜給我們
For to us a child is born
To us a son is given
政權必擔在他的肩頭上
他名稱為奇妙策士
全能的神
永在的父
和平的君
And his name shall be called
Wonderful Counselor
Mighty God
Everlasting Father
Prince of Peace
在耶穌出世之前的八百年
就有一個先知預言
就是神猜遣
祂自己的兒子來到世界
八百年前耶穌出生
當時有一個預言
說這個神會在地球上出現
當時在以塞亞的時代
那些以色列神的子民是博奕神
So in the time of Isaiah
他們是離棄神
寧願依靠人也不依靠神
They forsook God
They rather depended on people
But not God
以至到他們整個國家
陷入一個滅國的危機當中
So the whole country
The whole nation was decreasing
以色列民眾有一個很黑暗的時代
It was a very dark moment
Dark times for the Israel nation
他們很渴求一點點的光
They desire just a little bit of light
所以神就給他們這個應許
So God sent them this promise
叫他們不需要擔心
To let them know they don't need to worry
其實我們在今天來說
我們的心情應該是怎樣呢
So what are you feeling right now
就是幾天前我們去冬至的時候
每一年冬至就是全年最長的黑夜
So a few days ago it was winter solstice
It's actually the day with the longest darkness
這麼早天黑
你希望可以好像夏天一樣
日長夜短更好
The sun just dropped so early
You want it to be summer
You have lots of light
我們就在等
由前兩天開始
一直一直等到去春天
真的會有更多的光
更多的生氣
So would this be how you feeling now
From the two days before
And you are waiting up to spring
When there is more light and more light
因為我們今天就是從這一段經文
So let us today look at this verse
是神給一班神的子民的英許
This is a prophecy
This is a promise from God to His people
這班以色列的子民
好像我和你今天
可能是等著春天的來臨一樣
那種心情
The nation may be also waiting for this spring
Just like you and me
他的英許說有一個嬰孩
His promise says there is a child
有一個君王
There is a king
究竟我們可以從這段經文裡面
去怎樣學習
我們對今天有什麼意義
So what does this verse
have an effect on us today
我們一起在進入神的話語之前
我們再一次同心低頭祈禱
Let's pray
蔡恩主我們感謝祢
Father God thank you
讓我們有這段時間去研讀祢的話語
for giving us this time to look at your word
我們也特別感謝主祢的恩典
讓今天有五位弟兄姊妹受浸
加入你自己的身體
We especially thank you
for the five baptismal candidates
who are joining the body of Christ
求主祢的靈向我們說話
So may your spirit speak to us
叫我們明白祢對我們的心意
So that we understand your will
回應神祢的呼喚
And that we will respond
respond to your calling
祈禱奉主耶穌的名求
In Jesus name we pray
Amen
究竟嬰孩耶穌是我們在今天的今天
仍然覺得祂只是一個嬰孩
還是對你來說祂是一個君王
Do you still look at this baby
as simply a baby or king?
當聖誕卡寄給你的時候
你見到嬰孩很可愛
When you receive a Christmas card
there might be a baby on the card
and it must be cute
在馬槽裏面這個嬰孩又很卑微
But in the manger this baby is also very humble
祂好像真的沒有什麼力量
It seems that He is very vulnerable
He is very weak
但是這個嬰孩對於猶太人來說
是一個等候了很久的預言的實言
But this child is the fulfillment
of the promise that was long time ago
上個星期陳牧師和我們
在國語堂和粵語堂
分享了一個很重要的訊息
Last week at CSE and EMSE services
Pastor Allen shared with us a very important
大家其實都很熟悉三博士的故事
And of course you are very familiar
with the story of the wise man
其實當三博士見到一個星
就是猶太人的王
他就去尋找這個嬰孩
So the wise man, the magi
looked at a solid star
They pursued looking for this baby
對於這三博士來說
這個嬰孩是君王
So to these magi, the wise man
This baby is their king
但當他去到希律王那裏問的時候
這個希律王其實心裏面
只是看這個嬰孩就是一個嬰孩
But when the wise man went to Herod
King Herod just looked at this baby as a baby
他只是思想這個嬰孩
會不會威脅我的王位
He was just thinking
Would this baby be a threat to me?
有三學家說
其實人的本性
很多時候我們有一個
掌控佔有的慾望
Theologian says that
We human beings have a desire
to be empowered, to control
希律王他的佔有慾望
King Herod had this desire
to be empowered, to control
希望毀滅這個所謂
這三博士所說的猶太人的王
He needed to have this baby
or the king diminished
所以對希律來講
這個嬰孩就只不過是一個嬰孩
So to King Herod
This baby was simply a baby
就算他當年是君王
他現在就是沒有力量了
So even if this baby would have become a king
This time he was a baby weak
現在這個希律對於這個嬰孩來講
是可以為所欲為的
At this very moment
King Herod could do anything he wanted
但是三博士卻是
願意犧牲他的時間
還要長途跋涉
繼續去尋找耶穌
But the wise men
would be willing to sacrifice their time
to continue to seek this king
要犧牲自己一些的東西
Of course there's a lot of sacrifices
that they needed to make
當他找到耶穌的時候
他就將最好的獻上給耶穌
And when they saw
when they finally found this baby
they gave their best to them
所以我今天也想問你從這個三博士的故事裡面
究竟我們是希律去抗拒耶穌
只是看他一個嬰孩
真的不會有什麼大事可以做得出
在那個時候
還是我們知道他是一個君王
So let me ask you a question
With the story of this Magi
Is this baby simply a baby to you?
Or is he the king in your heart?
可能我們已經信了耶穌的弟兄姊妹會說
我當然知道他是嬰孩君王
Maybe some of our brothers and sisters Christians
will say of course he's my king
但究竟他是不是真的你的君王
Is he really your king?
還是你仍然將他放在馬槽裡面
仍然是一個嬰孩
Or are you still keeping him in the manger
in the stable
that he was still a baby?
從今天的經文裡面很清楚告訴我們
就是因有一位嬰孩為我們
就是為我和你而生的
有一子要賜給我們
This verse says it's really
clearly is for to us a child is born
to us a son is given
這個嬰孩耶穌
This baby Jesus
究竟他是誰呢?
Who is he?
我想弟兄姊妹或者朋友
你假若是未認識耶穌的
我想知道介紹這個耶穌給你認識
Friends if you have not known Jesus yet
I would like to introduce him to you
因為在菲律賓書2章6至8節這樣說
他說這個耶穌
他本有神的形象
卻是不堅持自己與神同等
反倒虛己
取了奴僕的形象
成為人的樣式
In Philippians it says
Who though he was in the form of God
do not count equality with God a thing to be grasped
but emptied himself by taking the form of a servant
being born in the likeness of men
神成為人的樣式
God being made in man's likeness
當你看這個嬰孩的時候
不是看普通平時看嬰孩
遲些他會長大成人
When you look at this baby
Don't look at this baby
Oh he is going to grow
而是你要看這個嬰孩耶穌這個嬰孩
是從一個充滿宇宙萬物的神
這麼偉大的
反而他縮小成為一個小的嬰孩
But when you look at this baby
He is the embodiment of God
of the universe coming in the form of this little baby
這個是最大的神蹟
This is the biggest miracle
在約翰福音
約翰福音在第一章十四節那裡說
他就是導成了肉身
住在我們中間
充滿了有因典有真理
我們也都見過他的榮光
正是負獨一而止的榮光
In the Gospel of John it says
And the Word became flesh
And dwell among us
And we have seen his glory
Glory as of the only Son from the Father
Full of grace and truth
一個很奇妙的神蹟
This is the very impressive miracle
神成為了人
God has become a man
並且經歷我們所經歷的
And he has experienced all that we experience
其實當他導成肉身的時候
不是他沒有了那個神的本性
It's not that when he became a man
and became a baby he lost his deity
或者沒有了神的本質
He didn't lose the nature of God
而是好像一個膜遮住了他的光
以致我們可以看得見他
But it's like a veil
It's like a cover
Just covering him that we can still see him
可能你都聽過耶穌曾經
在山上面登山變象
You might have heard the story
called the Transfiguration
他上到山上的時候
他和彼得亞哥約翰上到去
彼得亞哥約翰看都看不到
因為那些衣服他身上是發光的
So when Jesus went up to the mountain
with Peter John and James
It was so bright
It was full of his glory
and they couldn't even see him
就好像約翰福音經文所說的那種榮光
It's always like this gospel
This verse is saying
The glory of God is so bright
所以耶穌到神到成肉身
成為人來到
他是將自己包裹起
So God became a man
He was covering himself with a veil
以致我們能夠看得見他
So that we can actually see him
可以認識他 可以經歷他
So that we can know him and experience him
你再想一想
到成肉身的意思是怎樣呢
Think again
What is the meaning of incarnation
God became man
耶穌原本在天堂的寶座上面
甘願的到卑微的馬槽那裡
是成為一個被慰養的嬰孩
So he was first in the universe
He was sitting on the throne of the whole universe
But he came humbly
to be born as a baby in a manger
他原本可以用他的口中的話語
就可以維繫世界的運作
他說立就立
要成就就成就
Think of this
God sustains the world with just a word
他是甘願依賴一個年輕的婦人去慰養他
But he chose to be dependent
on the nourishment of a woman
我真的很想你想清楚這件事
I really want to ask you to really think about this
一個全能的神
在世界上面以一個無助的嬰孩來出現
This almighty God
has come in the form of this vulnerable baby
這是一個令人震驚的神蹟
This is shocking
那個能夠創造世界的神
成為一個受造的人
This is the God creator
who became one of us like the creation
那個無罪的經歷
罪惡的世界
He never experienced sin
He didn't sin
But he is in a simple world
那個無限的
成為有限的
He is infinite
But he became finite
那個不會扭壞的
成為了扭壞的
And this immortal experiences mortality
這個就是杜成玉身住在我們中間的奇蹟
This is the miracle of
Word became flesh dwelling among us
既然神藉著耶穌
這個嬰孩杜成玉身在我們當中
So God has sent His son Jesus
to come to us to dwell within us
祂要完成神一個什麼任務呢
What is the mission and the purpose
that He needs to fulfill
菲律賓書繼續說既有人的樣子就謙卑自己
全心順服
以致於死
並且死在十字架上
Philippians continue to say
And being found in human form
He humbled himself by becoming
obedient to the point of death
Even death on the cross
他有三樣東西可以成為我們的榜樣
There are three things that he can become our example
最少這三樣
At least these three things
他原先是神
但他卻願意謙卑自己
He is God
But he is willing to humble himself
他願意是順服
He is willing to be obedient
以致於犧牲自己
And he sacrificed himself
其實這個與人的本性是很大的分別
This is actually the opposite of a human nature
因為人的本性是以自己的利益為重心
Because human nature is self-centered and selfish
他是為了自己的好處
以及我們佔有慾去生活的
Humans always think of what I want
And if I am in control
這個嬰孩耶穌來到世界
釘在十字架上
無罪的代替了有罪的
以致我們能夠同樣的經歷他
在我們生命當中的改變
The baby Jesus has come to the world
His sinless body has taken the place of the sinful man
So that we can have life
今天有五位受浸的弟兄姊妹
So today we have these five brothers and sisters
who again are baptized
就因為他們經歷了神
在他們生命當中的作為
Because they have experienced
what God has done in their hearts and their lives
這個嬰孩的耶穌
This baby Jesus
成為人的樣式
Has become the likeness of man
希伯利書第四章十五十六節那裡說
因為我們的大祭司
這個大祭司就是
將神和人的關係可以恢復
就是耶穌將我們和神的關係恢復
並且不能
並非不能體恤我們的軟弱
換句話來說
耶穌是能夠體恤我們的軟弱
他也在各方面受過試探
與我們一樣
只是他沒有犯罪
所以我們只管坦然無懼地
來到他私恩的寶座前
唯要得憐憫 蒙恩慰
作及時的幫助
The passage Hebrews chapter 40 says
We don't have a priest who is out of touch
With our reality
This priest is the bridge between us and God
He has been through weakness and testing
Experienced it all
Like how we experienced it
All but the sin
So let's walk right up to him
And get what he is so ready to give
Take the mercy
Accept the help
當我們這樣理解耶穌的時候
So when we try to understand Jesus like this
我們多麼想耶穌繼續是一個嬰孩
How much we want Jesus
To continue to be like this baby
以致到祂只是體恤我們的軟弱
So that He can have mercy on our weaknesses
但我想問你的就是
But I want to ask you a question
在這個聖誕節我很想你答這個問題
I want you to answer this question
During this Christmas time
你是不是只有一個遷就你的耶穌
Do you just want an adjustable Jesus
這個耶穌祂是體會人世間的感情
挑戰 苦難
Because Jesus can understand our suffering
Understand all the challenges that we go through
沒錯 祂是會安慰我們
要明白我們
Yes, He can understand us
He can comfort us
我們軟弱跌倒
只要我們向祂認罪
祂就願意赦免我們
When we are weak
When we fall
As long as we confess
He will forgive us
有一個牧者
他說這個adjustable Jesus
我覺得這個遷就我們的耶穌
他講得很有意思
我覺得他講得有很多的提醒
There's a pastor who talked about adjustable Jesus
Is that only what we want?
And he said to the point
他說就是
好像我們大家可能有小朋友的父母
你們會知道他們小時候
十歲之前可能那個可塑性高一點
盡量希望教育他們成為一個怎樣的人
So this illustration goes like that
You know parents
You have parents
You have little children
So before ten you want to
Just try to give them anything
And mold them to someone that you want them to be
很多時我們當做這個
道成肉身的耶穌
那麼明白我們
就好像我們不多不少就將祂
不如都是好像
我們怎樣呢
讓祂遷就我們
So what this pastor is saying
When we look at Jesus
As an adjustable Jesus
Is that oh I can mold and shape Jesus
To whatever I want and whatever I need
或者調教我們自己的信仰
到一個比較寬鬆
比較沒有要求的耶穌
那個方向
Maybe I can alter a little of my faith
And on my walk with God
So that it will be loose
It's not too stressful
原來跟隨耶穌
耶穌說要真的付出犧牲的
跟隨祂是需要付代價的
我就不是很想這些
But when Jesus said
You follow me, you take up your cross
You follow me, maybe there are sacrifices
That you need to make
And we say oh maybe then
I might not want to follow too closely
或者我們對神的信心不足夠
我們就告訴祂
我是不夠信心的了
沒辦法了
Maybe when I am not
I don't have enough faith in God
Oh well it's just me
I really just don't have enough faith
其實我們很多時都會將耶穌
去遷就我們的狀況
我們的淑靈生命的情況
Maybe there are a lot of times
We really are trying to adjust Jesus
To fit into our mold
我們的生活方式
To fit into our lifestyle
我們的時間表
To fit into our schedule
我們的期望
To fit in our desires
耶穌真的明白的
Yes, Jesus does understand
祂愛我們的
Because He loves us
祂是體諒我們的
Because He has mercy on us
但是同樣
But the same thing
祂對我們也都有要求
He has demands on us
而我們需要回應
祂在我們生命當中的工作
And we need to respond
To the works He is working in us
我記得在很多年前
我讀完神學之後
在加拿大讀完神學
準備回香港
I remember I finished seminary
And then I was going to go back to Hong Kong
當年香港有一個股災
In that time
There was Hong Kong economic fall
大家都知道
有些不認識我的大英節目
都知道我家是做生意的
So some of the brothers and sisters
Know that I came from a business family
當時讀完讀神學的時候
剛剛有股災
儲了的錢差不多蒸發了
So during that time
The money that I saved
Almost all vanquished
並且就是想著
真的儲起錢來
然後讀神學
自己計劃好的事情
就覺得很安全很穩妥
就去走
I had a plan to have my savings
To support myself
To go to seminary
That was my plan
I thought it was pretty secure
但是到畢業的時候
發覺原來自己是負資產
But after I graduated
I found that I was below
有時人就需要在那個時刻裏面
決定究竟怎麽辦
So at that time
I had to think what to do
究竟耶穌要遷就我
還是我遷就耶穌
Is it that I want Jesus to adjust to me
Or do I continue to walk in His will
不如祂繼續為一個嬰孩
只是安慰我、照顧我、保護我
供應我就算了
Maybe it's good for him to stay as a baby
So that he can understand my weakness
Continue to provide and support me
當時我的小孩還很小
My kids were still young at that time
我們家裏還有一個樂趣
有一個角落就每天祈禱
My wife and I had a corner
That we prayed every day
就問神究竟應該快畢業了
回香港還是留在加拿大
We were asking God
Oh we are coming to an end
In my seminary training
Do I go back to Hong Kong
Or do I stay here
二十多年前
在加拿大
特別在加拿大中部生活很便宜
More than 20 years ago
I was in Calgary
And it was pretty
It was not expensive to live
負資產也不用太害怕
So even I didn't have much money
I didn't have to worry
我最記得一元就可以搞定
小孩的玩具
因為garage sale你走一圈之後
別人看到小孩這麼可愛
不用錢送給你
回家中途都是二手玩具
You know I can get the toys from garage sale
A dollar or two is so cheap
於是我回香港
就見教會裏面的執事
他們就問我
So I went to the church
And I asked the deacons
And they asked me
因為我們要決定
究竟回香港還是留在加拿大
我們都要知道
究竟回香港行不行得通
So I still had to know
If I go back to Hong Kong
Is there a way
回到香港
有個執事就問我
So when I go back to Hong Kong
There was a deacon asking me
我都很坦白告訴他
我負資產
I don't have much money
他說會不會一會兒
真的有些追債的上來
在教會裏面淋油
會很大件事
You know am I going to be
Chased with all my debts
我說我只知道三樣東西
And I said I only know three things
神呼召我
God has called me
神告訴我不要回頭
God told me not to look back
我又係負資產
And yes I'm in debt
咁佢又話畀我聽
咁不如你畀個
Business plan
即係經濟方案畀我
你幾時還曬你啲負資產
先請你啦
And he asked me
Ok when can you
Fill up all your debts
Then I will hire you after that
其實對我嚟講
我覺得好簡單嘅就係
如果佢咁諗啦
全個執事會都係咁諗啦
咁我就返加拿大
喺加拿大繼續侍奉囉
And in my mind
I say if he was thinking like this
And if the whole deacon board
Was thinking like this
I was just simply staying in Canada
好彩就只係一兩個執事係咁諗
Oh actually it was only
One or two deacons
佢有廿個執事
大部分都唔係咁諗
Out of twenty deacons
And most of them
Were not thinking like that
佢就淨係搞清楚
我嘅呼召同埋神嘅帶領
They were mainly asking me
To really clear up clarify
What my calling from God was
於是佢哋就邀請我返咗香港
亦都我就返咗香港
So they invited me back to Hong Kong
And that's when I went back to Hong Kong
其實呢個經歷呢
畀我一個好深刻嘅體會就係
And this experience has
It's a big impact on me
我哋每一個人都會喺唔同嘅
人生階段裏面
經歷一啲好特別嘅事情
Every one of us
Word go through different season of life
And experience different things
喺嗰個時刻
究竟我哋要耶穌
淨係就咗我嘅軟弱
還是我要打開我嘅心靈
去憑信心踏前一步
睇見佢嘅大能
And the question
The same question in every season of life is
Am I asking Jesus to adjust to me
Or am I continue to walk in faith
In the will of God
當我哋行出信心一步嘅時候
If I take a step of faith forward
呢個鷹鞋係我哋嘅軍王
This baby has become our king
我哋將我哋自己要掌控嘅都交畀佢
So what I have in control
I will give it to him
就跟隨佢每一步
I will continue to follow him step by step
佢就會畀我哋見到佢嘅大能
And he will show his power to us
因為經文裏面繼續講
政權必擔在佢嘅肩頭上
佢名稱為奇妙策士全能嘅神
永在一副和平嘅軍
The verse continues
The government will be on his shoulders
And his name shall be called the wonderful counselor
Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace
呢個係神嘅描述
This is the description of God
呢個鷹鞋係神
This baby is God
並且喺菲勒比書裏面就講
當耶穌願意能夠謙卑自己
以至於死成就神嘅計劃
去拯救我同你之後
When Jesus was willing to be humble
and sacrificed himself to save you and me
菲勒比書說神亦都同樣賜給耶穌
超乎萬名之上嘅名
使一切在天上嘅
地上嘅同埋地底下嘅
Therefore God has highly exalted him
and bestowed on him
the name that is above every name
因耶穌嘅名
縱膝都要跪下
縱口都要宣認
耶穌基督是主
歸榮耀給父神
So that at the name of Jesus
Every knee should bow
and in heaven and on earth
and under the earth
and every tongue confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord
to the glory of God the Father
究竟耶穌喺你心目中
喺你嘅心裏面真係
佢係一個君王
掌管你嘅生命
So in your heart
Is he really your king
taking hold of you
佢係萬名之上嘅名
Is his name above every other name
還是佢仍然喺個嬰孩
Or is he still a baby to you
如果佢喺你心目中
係一個君王嘅時候
If he is the king of yours
歌羅西書三章十節嗰度話
你就要穿上新人
呢個新人係照住
做佢嘅主嘅形象
喺知識上不斷地更新
Then Colossians says
and have put on this new self
which is being renewed in knowledge
after the image of its creator
所以神導成肉身成為人
但係人要成為神
成為耶穌嘅樣式
So as God has become a man
in man's likeness
we are to become like him as well
所以喺結束嘅時候
好想鼓勵大家
To wrap this up
I would like to encourage you
神今日發出一個邀請
God has sent you an invitation
你係咪願意毀身嘅
成為基督嘅樣式
Are you willing to surrender to him
to become more like him
特別今日受浸嘅大英展會
Especially the five brothers and sisters
對我哋每一個人嚟講
To every single one of us
喺你心目中佢係嬰孩
仍然喺馬槽裏面
還是佢係軍王掌管你嘅生命
In your heart ask yourself this question
Is Jesus still this baby
or is Jesus my king
神創造做人創造世界
God has created the heaven and the earth
人犯嘅罪
就係我哋嘅始早犯罪
墮落咗
Man has sinned
離開咗神
Man has departed from God
於是神要渡成肉身
嚟拯救我哋
So God has to become a man
in order to save man
呢個拯救嘅意思
就係我哋能夠成為主耶穌基督嘅樣式
我哋嘅生命係更加嘅豐盛
The salvation means that we can become
like our Lord Jesus Christ
and alive can become more abundant
願意我哋認定呢位耶穌
係我哋嘅軍王
讓我哋聖誕改變生命嘅奇蹟
因為呢個bb
就係渡成肉身嚟到世界
去改變我哋同你嘅生命
成為我哋一生嘅經歷
同埋一個永恆嘅盼望
So let us acknowledge that Jesus is our King
Allowing the miracle of Christmas
to transform our lives
Becoming an experience and eternal hope
Throughout our lives
我哋一齊同心低頭祈禱
Let's pray
所祈恩主
Lord thank you
當我哋嚟到你嘅面前嘅時候
我哋真係好需要你嘅憐憫
When we come before you we need your mercy and compassion
我哋承認自己嘅軟弱
We acknowledge that we are sinful and we are weak
甚至我哋冇辦法完全嘅信靠你
And we know that we cannot completely trust you
你作為嬰孩渡成肉身你係明白我哋
When you became a baby
Became a man you understand us
但係你卻係叫我哋唔好停留咗喺嗰度
But you told us not to stay there
你願意同我哋一齊同行
You are willing to walk with us
明白我哋體會我哋嘅體恤我哋嘅同時
又激勵我哋幫助我哋去成為主理嘅樣式
While you understand our weaknesses
And what we go through
You continue to encourage us
To become more like you
求你叫我哋願意毀身嘅
唔係要你遷就我哋
而係我哋去遷就你
May you help us to really surrender to you
So that we are not having an adjustable Jesus
Adjusting to what we need
But we come on to you
And to take your will into our lives
祈禱奉祝阿蘇哥的命靠
In Jesus' name we pray
Amen